{"tossups": [{"question": "At this battle, Sam Houston received a lifelong wound from an enemy arrow. After this battle, John Gordon reported British collaboration with the enemy leading to the capture of Pensacola. Menawa led the losing force of this battle, after which over 23 million acres of land were given to the U.S. in the Treaty of Fort Jackson. This battle in what is today Alabama was fought against the Red Stick Confederacy. For ten points, name this 1814 battle in which Andrew Jackson routed the Creek.", "answer": "Battle of<em><b> Horseshoe Bend</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In this city in 1958, people who witnessed an argument between Majbritt Morrison and her Jamaican husband assaulted Morrison, an act that resulted in a week-long race riot. After Stephen Lawrence, a teenaged black youth, was murdered in this city, the Macpherson report denounced this city\u2019s\u201cinstitutionally racist\u201d police force. Following the passage of the Community Charge, the largest protests against that tax took place in, for ten points, what city where 1958 race riots struck Notting Hill?", "answer": "<em><b> London</b></em>, England, U(nited) K(ingdom)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "During this conflict, the Halloween Massacre occurred after a disputed result in the 1992 presidential election. The Battle of Cuito Cuanavale during this war was the largest battle on African soil since World War Two, and Paul Manafort worked to portray UNITA leader Jonas Savimbi favorably during this war. Fidel Castro sent Cuban troops to aid one side in this war, fought between UNITA and Jose dos Santos\u2019s MPLA. For ten points, name this African war fought over a former Portuguese colony.", "answer": "<em><b> Angolan Civil</b></em> War", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "An unachieved goal of this program was the creation of over 800,000 housing units under Title III of this program\u2019s Housing Act. This program also opposed a 1947 piece of legislation that this program\u2019s presidential overseer called a \u201cslave-labor\u201d bill. The settlement of the Lend-Lease program that had been run by the previous president was one of this program\u2019s major goals. Attempting to preserve the agenda of the New Deal, for ten points, name this liberal program outlined by Harry Truman.", "answer": "<em><b> Fair Deal</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "For the grand opening of Lincoln Center, this dancer choreographed the premiere of Samuel Barber\u2019s Antony and Cleopatra. This man, who was mentored by Lester Horton, founded a company that was taken over by Judith Jamison after this man\u2019s death from AIDS. This man\u2019s best-known work was presented at the inaugurations of Jimmy Carter and Bill Clinton. Inspired by spirituals, gospel, and blues music, for ten points, name this African-American choreographer of Revelations.", "answer": "Alvin<em><b> Ailey</b></em> Page 1", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Dance"}, {"question": "A copy of this speech was once smuggled in a basket of women\u2019s underwear so that dissenters could not destroy it before it was read. In order to secure a \u201cgrand peace for all the generations,\u201d this speech asked listeners to \u201c[endure] the unendurable and [suffer] what is unsufferable.\u201d This speech marked the first occasion that common citizens heard the voice of their emperor, who signaled a desire to surrender after facing the atom bomb. For ten points, identify this speech given by Hirohito at the end of World War Two.", "answer": "<em><b> Jewel Voice</b></em> Broadcast (accept<em><b> Imperial Rescript on the Termination of the Greater </b><b>East Asia War</b></em>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This figure\u2019s daughter, Pearl, wrote her epitaph, \u201cThe gem that filled [the casket] sparkles yet.\u201d An 1886 photograph shows Blue Duck posing next to this figure. \u201cHanging Judge\u201d Isaac Parker gave this figure a nine-month prison sentence for stealing a horse. Edgar Watson is among the suspects in the still unsolved 1889 murder of this figure who knew the James and Younger boys while growing up in Missouri. James Reed and Jim July were among the husbands of, for ten points, what outlaw queen of the Wild West?", "answer": "Belle<em><b> Starr</b></em>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Short Fiction"}, {"question": "This empire was established after the Battle of Ongal by Asparukh of the Dulo clan, who founded its first capital of Pliska. One ruler of this state, Simeon I the Great, established his dominance by defeating Leo Phocas at the Battle of Achelous. This state was destroyed after the Battle of Kleidion was won by Basil II, whose epithet comes from blinding 99 out of 100 survivors from this empire\u2019s army. For ten points, name this western neighbor of the Byzantine Empire.", "answer": "First<em><b> Bulgaria</b></em>n Empire", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In this city, the Black Recondos were given permission by the police to carry out arrests. Sojourner Truth moved to this city after she escaped from slavery, and Jack Johnson was arrested in this city for violating the Mann Act. C. W. Post invented Grape Nuts and founded a cereal company in this city, where W. K. Kellogg also made \u201ccorn flakes.\u201d The Race Betterment Foundation was founded in this city by a eugenicist doctor. John Harvey Kellogg founded a sanitarium in, for ten points, what Michigan city?", "answer": "<em><b> Battle Creek</b></em>, Michigan", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The similarities between George Downie\u2019s misfortunes in this battle and Horatio Nelson\u2019s fortunes in Egypt led this battle to be known as the \u201cFalse Nile.\u201d The Saranac River was a key location at this battle, where the flagship of the winning side was the 26-gun USS Saratoga. Thomas MacDonough crushed George Prevost\u2019s troops at this battle. For ten points, name this battle of the War of 1812 in which the British gave up Plattsburgh in upstate New York, because they lost control of a lake on the Canadian border.", "answer": "Battle of<em><b> Lake Champlain</b></em> (accept Battle of<em><b> Plattsburgh</b></em> before mentioned) Page 2", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "John Nicolas Choate created many glass pale negative images of this institution. While recruiting students, this institution\u2019s founder noted that people called Washichu were militarily successful because of their education. Luther Standing Bear served as a recruiter for this school, which was founded by Richard Henry Pratt, who attempted to \u201cKill the Indian: Save the Man.\u201d For ten points, name this Pennsylvania boarding school whose football team was led by two-time Olympic gold-medalist Jim Thorpe.", "answer": "<em><b> Carlisle</b></em> Indian Industrial School (accept<em><b> United States Indian Industrial</b></em> School)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Gorgidas was the first leader of this group, which had taken a deliberately relaxed stance under Charbrias. At a battle where one side used an oblique order and forced its right wing back, this group was led by Pelopidas to counter the Spartan right wing. This group, which was stationed in Cadmia, was decimated at Chaeronea by Philip II\u2019s phalanxes. Epaminondas\u2019s army at Leuctra relied on, for ten points, what elite force of the Theban army that consisted of 150 pairs of male lovers?", "answer": "<em><b> Sacred Band</b></em> of Thebes", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "A kingdom in this modern-day country killed war captives in a ceremony known as the Annual Customs, which were started under King Agaja. Sky kings called Ogiso legendarily ruled over an empire named for this present-day country that created a mask of Queen Mother Idia. King Houegbadja began an all-female military regiment in this modern-day country called the Amazons. The last king of a certain kingdom in this country, Behanzin, was defeated by the French in 1894. For ten points, name this country, home to the Fon people.", "answer": "Republic of<em><b> Benin</b></em>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "A Harper\u2019s Weekly cartoon depicting this man seated in front of a paper while Jefferson Davis stands aside dressed as Iago is titled \u201cTime Does Wonders.\u201d This man served as a chaplain at the Battle of Vicksburg and replaced Albert G. Brown in a position that had remained open for eight years. That position was won by this man in an 1870 election in Mississippi, the result of which was described as a\u201cweakening blow against color line prejudice.\u201d For ten points, name this first African-American to serve in Congress.", "answer": "Hiram Rhodes<em><b> Revels</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The central vessel in this event was captained by Luke Collingwood and had a destination of Black River, a location that today contains a monument commemorating the victims of this event. Granville Sharp was informed of this event by Olaudah Equiano and attempted to press murder charges on the crew of the central vessel. This 1781 event was a major symbol of the inhumane conditions of the Middle Passage. J.M.W. Turner\u2019s painting The Slave Ship was inspired by, for ten points, what massacre?", "answer": "<em><b> Zong</b></em> Massacre", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This leader prevented the Morho Naba, the chief of the Mossi people, from holding courts to consolidate power for the Committees for the Defense of the Revolution. This man made the Renault 5 the official service car of his ministers, and he fought the Christmas War against Mali over the Agacher Strip. This successor of Jean-Baptiste Ouedraogo was assassinated in a 1987 coup d\u2019etat. Nicknamed \u201cAfrica\u2019s Che Guevara,\u201d For ten points, name this Socialist, the first president of Burkina Faso and last president of Upper Volta.", "answer": "Thomas<em><b> Sankara</b></em>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This theologian argued that the West\u2019s position of \u201canti-communism\u201d is \u201can evil even greater than communism itself.\u201d This theologian was influenced by Charlotte von Kirschbaum while a student at Gottingen. This theologian\u2019s Barmen Declaration was adopted by Christians in Nazi Germany to resist the German Christian Movement. This theologian\u2019s best known work is sometimes titled Romans II. For ten points, name this Swiss reformed theologian, who authored the Church Dogmatics.", "answer": "Karl<em><b> Barth</b></em>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "This faction put Amadeo, the Duke of Aosta, on the throne after the battle of Alcolea. Tomas de Zumalacarregui was a commander of this faction and inspired his country\u2019s national breakfast dish, tortillas. The first war named for this faction was ended by the Convention of Vergara. Isabella II was overthrown by members of this faction, named for a prince who was removed from succession through the Pragmatic Sanction of 1830. For ten points, name these 19th century Spanish wars, named for an Infante.", "answer": "<em><b> Carlist</b></em>s (accept<em><b> Carlism</b></em>, accept First, Second, or Third<em><b> Carlist</b></em> Wars)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A section of this work examining \u201cDemocracy in the Three Main Fields\u201d warns against \u201cultra-democracy\u201d which arises from individualistic aversion to discipline. This work claims that Blacks in the United States are oppressed by a reactionary ruling class as opposed to workers or farmers. This work\u2019s section on \u201cWar and Peace\u201d states that, \u201cEvery Communist must grasp the truth; political power grows out of the barrel of a gun.\u201d For ten points, name this 1964 book that contains sayings from a Communist leader of China.", "answer": "<em><b> Little Red</b></em> Book (accept<em><b> Quotations from Chairman Mao Tse-tung</b></em>, accept<em><b> Mao </b><b>Zhuxi Yulu</b></em>)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "At this battle, George H. Thomas refused to assault Confederate forces, saying, \u201cOne or two more such assaults would use up this army.\u201d Sherman attempted to capture Pigeon Hill at this battle during his advance on Joseph Johnston. This battle names a man who presided over a trial of 113 IWW members in 1917. That man with this name also banned \u201cShoeless Joe\u201d Jackson after a 1919 scandal. For ten points, name this battle, which also names the first baseball commissioner who banned the Black Sox.", "answer": "Battle of<em><b> Kennesaw Mountain</b></em> (accept<em><b> Kenesaw Mountain</b></em> Landis)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>The excessive number of bathrooms at this location contributed to its nickname,\u201cBoldt\u2019s Folly.\u201d An ostentatious Versailles-themed 1897 ball organized at this location by Mrs. Bradley Martin is an example of its city\u2019s wealth inequality. After serving as president, (+) Herbert Hoover spent over three decades living in this building, whose restaurants include Peacock Alley and The Bull and Bear Steakhouse. One namesake of this Fifth Avenue building is considered the first self-made (*) </b> millionaire in the United States, largely from his success in fur trading. For ten points, name this luxury hotel in New York City.", "answer": "<em><b> Waldorf Astoria</b></em> New York", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>One side in this battle positioned themselves with the capture of Vezon and Bourgeon. After he failed to attack the Redoubt d\u2019Eu in this battle, Richard Ingoldsby was court martialed. A Voltaire story of this battle notes that the men of Charles Hay and the Comte (+) d\u2019Auteroche both refused to fire the first shots upon one another. Louis XV watched this battle, which the Duke of Cumberland initiated to defend Tournai from (*)</b> Maurice de Saxe\u2019s forces. For ten points, name this 1745 battle of the War of the Austrian Succession that allowed France to conquer the Netherlands.", "answer": "Battle of<em><b> Fontenoy</b></em>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>During this war, \u201cPatriotic Soup\u201d was created and is now part of Chaozhou cuisine. In this war, trebuchet designs were copied from those used in the Sacking of Baghdad. Following this war, two emperors fled south to what is now Hong Kong, and after losing this war, (+) Lu Xiufu and Zhao Bing jumped off a cliff into the sea. Bayan led one side during this war, which included a six-year siege during the Battle of Xiangyang. The Battle of (*) </b>Yamen took place in, for ten points, what war in which Mongke Khan died at the Battle of Diaoyu Castle, leading to Kublai Khan\u2019s rule over China?", "answer": "<em><b> Yuan-Song</b></em> war(s) (accept<em><b> Mongol Conquest</b></em> (or invasion) of the<em><b> Song</b></em> Dynasty or equivalents)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>This speech listed \u201cyou don\u2019t see the people enough anymore\u201d among the \u201ctypical comments\u201d its speaker got while on a ten-day retreat to Camp David. Most of the ideas in this speech were inspired by the input of pollster Pat Caddell. The first Secretary of (+) Energy, James R. Schlesinger, was fired after this speech, which was given in response to an economic recession. This speech asked people to use carpools and public transportation, and claimed that America was facing a (*)</b> \u201ccrisis of confidence\u201d caused in part by the Iranian Revolution. For ten points, name this speech given during the 1979 oil crisis by Jimmy Carter.", "answer": "<em><b> Malaise</b></em> speech (accept \u201c<em><b>Crisis of Confidence</b></em>\u201d speech before mentioned) Page 10", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man\u2019s wife, Zuzana Honschova, lived in the United States until her death in 1815. Exiled by Russia to Kamchatka for his involvement in the Confederation of Bar, this man asked King Louis XV of France for assistance in establishing a colony. In 1776, after having established a colony at Antongil Bay, this man became Ampansacabe of an (+) African island. After fighting alongside his former comrade Pulaski in the American Revolution, this man died fighting the French in 1786 in (*)</b> Madagascar. For ten points, name this eccentric Slovak nobleman, who declared himself King of Madagascar.", "answer": "John (Janos)<em><b> Zapolya</b></em>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>This project was initially led by British soldier and geographer, William Lambton, and started at Cape Comorin. This project began shortly after an 1800 military conflict that ended in the defeat of the Tiger of Mysore, Tipu Sultan. This project found that (+) Kanchenjunga was actually shorter than another feature named for one of this project\u2019s leaders, George Everest. This project included Gujarat and Bengal in its map of areas (*) </b>owned by the British East India Company. For ten points, name this 19th century scientific project that measured an Asian subcontinent\u2019s size.", "answer": "<em><b> Great Trigonometrical Survey</b></em> (prompt on \u201cSurvey of India\u201d)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>An expedition in this war led by General Pedro de Villasur was ended by a group of Pawnee. The first presidio of Pensacola was destroyed and Nassau in the Bahamas was plundered during this war. Charles XII\u2019s death foiled the efforts of Irish exile, James FitzJames Butler, to incite a (+) Jacobite rising during this war. This war led to the dismissal of cardinal and chief minister, Giulio Alberoni. The aggressor in this war failed to overturn the (*) </b> Peace of Utrecht. For ten points, name this war in which a certain number of countries affirmed the terms of the War of the Spanish Succession.", "answer": "War of the<em><b> Quadruple Alliance</b></em> Page 11", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A billion dollars has been allocated to clean up duckweed (*) </b> infestation in this body of water. Because this body of water reminded Amerigo Vespucci of an Italian city, he gave the surrounding country its name. For ten points, name this large, South American lake.", "answer": "Lake<em><b> Maracaibo</b></em> (accept Lago de<em><b> Maracaibo</b></em>)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b>James Wilkinson drunkenly exposed a central letter sent by the namesake of this group, who resigned from one post after a promotion was given to Baron de Kalb. The men involved in this group were accused of being \u201cCandle snuffers, Shifters of scene and Mutes\u201dby Henry (+) Laurens. The namesake of this group led forces to victory at Brandywine in the same year that the Battle of Saratoga had been won by (*) </b> Horatio Gates, who this group may have intended to promote. For ten points, name this group that attempted to oust George Washington as commander-in-chief of the Continental Army.", "answer": "<em><b> Conway Cabal</b></em> ", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>In 1964, a flight of this airline leaving Nairobi marked the Boeing 747\u2019s first air accident. In 2015, a subsidiary of this airline experienced a devastating crash caused by a pilot deemed \u201cunfit to work\u201d due to suffering from depression. Supporters of (+) Black September conducted a hijacking of this airline\u2019s Flight 615 in 1972 in an attempt to free prisoners. Those prisoners had committed a crime at an (*) </b> athletic event in the same country as that in which this airline is headquartered. For ten points, name this largest airline by revenue in Europe.", "answer": "Deutsche<em><b> Lufthansa</b></em> AG", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}], "bonuses": []}